<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The order of the communion</title>
            <title>Order of the Communion. 1548</title>
            <author>Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06057</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16457</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122099</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857251</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857251</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22944</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06057)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22944)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 55:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The order of the communion</title>
                  <title>Order of the Communion. 1548</title>
                  <author>Church of England.</author>
                  <author>Wied, Hermann von. Simplex ac pia deliberatio.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>The eyght daie of Marche, in the second yere of the reigne of our souereigne lorde kyng Edvvard the. VI: by Rychard Grafton printer to his moste royall Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>In the yere of our Lorde. M.D.XLVIII. [1548]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Based in part on: Wied, Hermann von.  Simplex ac pia deliberatio.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ C² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:22944:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22944:1"/>
            <p>¶ The or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22944:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:22944:2"/>
            <head>The proclamation.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Dward by the grace of God Kyng of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and Irelande, defendor of the faithe, &amp; of the churche of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland and Ireland in erthe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupreme hed: To al and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier our louing ſubiectis, Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>for ſo muche as in our high Courte of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, lately holden at Weſtmynſter, it was by vs wyth the conſent of the Lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and Commons there aſſembled moſte godly and agreably to Chriſtes holy inſtitution enacted, that the mooſte bliſſed Sacrament of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body and bludde of our ſauiour Chriſt ſhould from thenſfurthe be commonly deliuered and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred vnto all perſonnes within out Realme of Englande and Ireland, and other our dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vnder bothe kyndes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, of breade &amp; wyne, (except neceſſitie other wayes requyre) leaſt euery man phantaſiyng and deuiſyng a ſondry way by hymſelf, in the vſe of thys moſte bliſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of vnitie, there myghte thereby ariſe any vnſemely and vngodly diuerſitie: Our pleaſure is by thaduiſe of our mooſt deere vncle the Duke of Somerſett, gouernour of our parſon, &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector of al our Realmes, dominions &amp; ſubiectes, and other of our preuye Counſaill, that the ſayde bleſſed Sacrament be miniſtred vnto our people only after ſuche fourme and maner as hereafter, by our aucthoritie, with thaduiſe before mencio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:22944:3"/> is ſet furthe and declared: Willyng euery man with due reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and chriſtian behaueour, to come to this holye Sacramente and mooſte bleſſed Communion, leſt that by the vnworthye receauing of ſo hygh miſteries, they become giltie of the body and bludde of the Lord, and ſo eate &amp; drincke their awne damnation: but rather dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently triyng themſelfes, that they maye ſo come to this holy table of Chriſte, and ſo be partakers of this holy Communion, that they may dwell in Chriſte, and haue Chriſte dwellyng in them: And alſo wyth ſuche obedience and conformitie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue this our ordinaunce, and mooſte godly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, that wee may be encouraged from tyme to tyme, further to trauell for the reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſettyng furthe of ſuche godly ordres, as maye be mooſt to goddes glory, the edifiyng of our ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes, and for thaduauncement, of true religion. Whiche thinge, wee (by the help of God) mooſte erneſtly entende to bryng to effecte: Willyng all our louing ſubiectes in the meane tyme, to ſtay and quyet themſelfes, wyth this our direction, as men content to followe aucthoritie (accordyng to the bounde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> duety of ſubiectes,) and not enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng to ronne afore, and ſo by their raſhenes, be come the greateſt hynderers of ſuch thynges, as they more arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly then godly, wolde ſeme (by their awne priuat aucthoritie) mooſte hotly to ſet forwarde. Wee woulde not haue our ſubiectes ſo much to myſlike our Iudgement, ſo muche to miſtruſte our zeale, as though wee eyther coulde not diſcerne what were to be doen, or woulde not
<pb facs="tcp:22944:3"/> do all thinges in due tyme: God be prayſed, wee knowe bothe what by his wourde is mete to be redreſſed, and haue an erneſt mynd, by the aduiſe of our mooſt deere vncle, and other of our priuey Counſail, with all diligence and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient ſpede ſo to ſett furthe the ſame, as it maye mooſte ſtand wyth goddes glory, and edifying and quyetnes of our people: Whiche wee doubt not, but all our obedient and louing ſubiectes, will quyetly and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently tary for.</p>
            <closer>¶ God ſaue the Kyng.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="order_of_the_Communion">
            <pb facs="tcp:22944:4"/>
            <head>The order of the Communion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Yrſte the perſonne, Vicar or curat, the next Sonday or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly day, or at the leaſt one day before he ſhall miniſter the Communion, ſhal geue war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng to his paryſſhioners, or thoſe whyche be preſent that they prepare them ſelfes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſaiyng to them ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lte and plainlte as herafter followeth, or ſuch lyke.</p>
            <q>
               <p>DEre frendes, and you eſpecially, vpon whoſe ſoules I haue cure and charge, vpon <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap> daye next I doe ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de by Godes grace to offer to all ſuche as ſhalbe therto godlie dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the body and bloude of Chryſte, to be taken of them in the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of his moſt fruictfull and gloryous paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: By the which paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teuied remiſſion of our ſynnes, and be made partakers of the kyngdom of heuen, wherof, we be aſſured &amp; aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned yf we come to the ſayd Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with hartye repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for our
<pb facs="tcp:22944:4"/> offences, ſtedfaſt faith in Godes mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, and earneſt mynde to obey godes wyll, and to offend no more: wherfore our duety is, to come to theſe holy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries with moſt harty thankes to be geuen to almightye God, for his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercy and benefites, geuen &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon vs, his vnworthye ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes, for whome he hath not only geuen his body to death and ſhed his bludde, but alſo dothe voucheſaufe in a Sacrament, and myſterye, to geue vs his ſaid body &amp; bloud ſpiritually, to fede and drynke vpon. The whych Sacrament, being ſo diuine and holy a thynge, and ſo comfortable to them whych receaue it worthelye, &amp; ſo dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to them that will preſume to take the ſame vnworthely: my duty is to exhorte you, in the meane ſeaſon, to conſyder the greatnes of the thynge, and to ſearche &amp; examyne your awne conſciences, and that not lightlie, nor after the maner of dyſſimulers wyth god: But as they which ſhould come
<pb facs="tcp:22944:5"/> to a moſt godly and heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lie banket: not to come, but in the maryage gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, requyred of God in ſcripture, that you maye ſo muche as lyeth in you, be founde worthie to come to ſuche a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: The wayes &amp; meanes therto is.</p>
               <p>Fyrſt, that you be truly repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of your former euell life, and that you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe wyth an vnfayned harte to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghtie god your ſynnes &amp; vnkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes towardes his Maieſtye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted eyther by wil, worde or dede, infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie or ignoraunce, and that wyth inwarde ſorowe and teares, you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayle your offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, and requier of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightye god, mercy, and pardon, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing to him, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the botome of your hartes, thamendment of your former life. And emonges all others, Iam co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of God, eſpecially to moue &amp; exhorte you, to reconcile your ſelfs to your neyghbours, whome you haue offended, or who hath offended you, puttyng out of your hartes, alhatered
<pb facs="tcp:22944:5"/> and malyce againſt them, and to be in loue and charyte wyth all the worlde &amp; to forgeue other, as you would that God ſhould forgeue you. And if there be any of you, whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and greued in any thing, lacking comforte or counſaile, let him come to me, or to ſome other dyſcrete &amp; learned prieſt taught in the lawe of God, and confeſſe and open his ſynne and grief ſecretlie, that he maye receaue ſuche ghoſtlie counſaile, aduiſe, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte, that his conſcience maye be releued, and that of vs as a miniſter of God &amp; of the church, he may receaue comfort and abſolution to the ſatiſfaction of his mynde and auoyding of al ſcruple and doubtfulnes: requyring ſuche as ſhalbe ſatiſfied with a generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, not to be offended with them that doth vſe, to their further ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiyng, thauriculer and ſecret confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſt, nor thoſe alſo, which think nedeful or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient for the quyetnes of their awne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences, particulerly to
<pb facs="tcp:22944:6"/> the Lord. Let your mynd be without deſier to ſynne: Repent you trulie for your ſinnes paſt, haue an earneſt and lyuely faith in Chriſt, our ſauiour, be in perfect charytie wyth all men, ſo ſhal ye be mete partakers of theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſteries: But aboue all thynges you muſte geue moſt humble &amp; hartye thankes to God the father, the ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, &amp; the holy ghoſt, for the redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world, by the deathe and paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſauiour Chriſt both God &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who dyd humble him ſelf euen to the deathe vpon the croſſe for vs miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſynners, liyng in darknes and the ſhadowe of death, that he might ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vs the children of God, and exalte vs to euerlaſtyng life. And to thende that wee ſhoulde alwaye remember the excedyng loue of our Maſter and onlie ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt thus doi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g for vs, and the innumerable benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes which by his precyous bloud ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, he hath obteyned to vs, he hath lefte i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe holy miſteries as a pledge
<pb facs="tcp:22944:6"/> of hys loue, and a contynuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of the ſame, his awne bleſſed body and precyous bloud, for vs ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually to fede vpon, to our endles comforte and conſolation. To hym therefore wyth the father and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt, let vs geue, as wee are moſt bounden, contynual thankes, ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng our ſelfes wholy to his holy wyl &amp; pleaſure, and ſtudiyng to ſerue hym in true holynes and righteouſnes all the dayes of our life. Amen.</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶ Then the prieſt ſhall ſay to them which be redy to take the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>
               <q>If any man here be an open blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, aduouterer, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> malice, or enuy, or any other notable cryme, &amp; be not truly ſory therefore, &amp; earneſtlye myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to leaue the ſame vyces, or that doth not truſt himſelf to be reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyled to almightye God, &amp; in charyte with all the worlde, let him yet a whyle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayle his ſynnes &amp; not come to thys holy table, leaſt after the taki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of this moſte bleſſed breade, the deuell enter
<pb facs="tcp:22944:7"/> into him, as he dyd into Iudas, to fulfill in him all iniquite, and to bring him to deſtruction, bothe of body and ſoule.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Heare the prieſt ſhal pawſe a while, to ſee yf any man will wythdrawe hym ſelfe: and if he percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue any ſo to do, then let hym common wyth hym pryuely at conuement leaſure, and ſee whether he can wyth good exhortacion, bring him to grace: &amp; after a lytle pauſe, the prieſt ſhal ſay.</p>
            <p>
               <q>You that do trulie and earneſtlie repent you of your ſynnes, and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, commytted to almyghtie God, &amp; be in loue and charytie wyth your neyghbours, and entende to leade a newe life and hartelye to followe the commaundementes of God, and to walke from henſforthe in his holye waies, drawe nere, and take this holy Sacrament to your comforte, make your humble confeſſion to almightye God, and to his holy church, here ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered to gether, in hys name, mekely kneling vpon your knees.</q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22944:7"/>
            <p> Then ſhall a generall confeſſion be made in the name of al thoſe that are mynded to receyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Communion, either by one of them, or els by one of the miniſters, or by the prieſt hymſelf, all kneelyng humbly vpon their knees.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Almyghtie God, father of our lord Ieſus Chriſte, maker of all thinges, iudge of all men, wee knowlege and bewayle our manyfolde ſynnes and wyckednes, whyche we from tyme to tyme, moſt greuouſlie haue commyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by thought, worde, and dede, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy diuine maieſtie, prouoking moſt iuſtlye, thy wrath and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion againſt vs: wee doe earneſtlie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and be hartely ſory, for theſe our myſdoinges: The remembraunce of them is greuouſe vnto vs, the burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them is intollerable, haue mercy vpon vs, haue mercy vpon vs, moſte mercyfull father, for thy ſonne our Lord Ieſus Chriſtes ſake: Forgeue vs al that is paſt, and graunt that we maye euer hereafter, ſerue and pleaſe the, in newnes of life to the honour &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:22944:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22944:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22944:9"/> glorye of thy name, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then ſhall the prieſt, ſtand vp, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng hym to the people, ſay thus.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Our bleſſed Lord, who hath left po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to his churche, to abſolue penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſynners, from their ſynnes, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore to the grace of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lye father ſuche as trulie beleue in Chriſt, haue mercy vpon you, pardon and delyuer you, from al ſynnes, confyrme and ſtrength you in al goodnes, &amp; bryng you to euerlaſtyng life.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then ſhall the prieſt ſtande vp, and turnynge him toward the people, ſay thus:</p>
            <p>Here what comfortable woordes our ſauiour Chriſt ſaith to all that trulie turne to hym.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Come vnto me al that trauail and be heauy loden, and I ſhall refreſhe you. So God loued the world that he gaue his onlie begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that all that beleue in hym, ſhoulde not peryſhe, but haue life euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here alſo what S. Paule ſayth.</p>
            <p>
               <q>This is a true ſaiyng, and worthy
<pb facs="tcp:22944:9"/> of all men to be embraced and recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that Ieſus Chriſt came into this world to ſaue ſynners.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Heare alſo what S. Iohn ſayth.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Yf any man ſynne, wee haue an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate wyth the father, Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, he it is that obtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned grace for our ſinnes.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then ſhall the prieſt kneele doune and ſaye in the name of all them that ſhall receaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, this prayer followyng.</p>
            <p>
               <q>WE do not preſume to come to this thy table (O mercyful Lord) tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in our awne ryghteouſnes, but in thy manifold and greate mercyes: we be not worthie ſo muche as to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vp the cro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes vnder thy table: But thou arte the ſame Lord, whoſe propertye is alwayes, to haue mercy: Graunt vs therefore gracious Lorde ſo to eate the fleſhe, of thy dere ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, and to drynk his bloud in theſe holy miſteries, that we maye continually dwell in hym, and he in vs, that oure ſynfull bodyes, maye be
<pb facs="tcp:22944:10"/> made cleane by his body, and our ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les waſhed through his moſt precious bloud. Amen.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then ſhall the prieſt riſe, the people ſtill reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentlie knelyng, and the prieſte ſhall deliuer the Communion, firſt to the miniſters, if any be there preſent, that thei maie be redy to helpe the prieſt, and after to the other. And when he dooth deliuer the Sacrament, of the body of Chriſte, he ſhall ſay to euery one, theſe wordes followyng.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The bodye of oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, whiche was geuen for the, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue thy body vnto euerlaſtyng life.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And the prieſt delyuering the Sacrament, of the bloud, and geuyng euery one to drynke once and no more, ſhall ſaye.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The bloude of oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, which was ſhed for the, preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue thy ſoule vnto euerlaſtyng life.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If there be a deacon or other prieſt, then ſhall he followe with the Chalyce, and as the prieſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtreth the breade, ſo ſhall he for more expedicion miniſter the wine, in forme before wrytten.</p>
            <p>Then ſhal the prieſt, turnyng him to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, let the people dep<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt with this bleſſynge.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22944:10"/>
            <p>
               <q>The peace of God whiche paſſeth all vnderſtandyng, kepe your hartes and myndes in the knowlege and loue of God, and of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſte, our Lorde.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To the whiche the people ſhall anſwere.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Amen.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Note, that the breade that ſhalbe conſecrated ſhalbe ſuche as heretofore hath bene accuſtomed. And euery of the ſayd conſecrated breades, ſhalbe broken in twoo peces, at the leaſt, or more, by the diſcretion of the miniſtre, and ſo diſtributed. And men muſt not thynke, leſſe to be receiued in part, then in the whole, but in eche of theim the whole body of our ſauiour Ieſu Chryſt.</p>
            <p>Note, that yf it dothe ſo chaunce, that the wyne halowed and conſecrate dooth not ſuffice or bee ynough for theim that dooe take the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, the prieſte after the firſte Cuppe or Chalice be emptied, may go again to the aulter, and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentlie, and deuoutlie, prepare, and conſecrate an other, and ſo the thirde, or more lykewyſe, begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng at theſe woordes, <hi>Simili modo, poſtquam ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natum eſt,</hi> and endyng at theſe woordes, <hi>qui pro nobis &amp; pro multis effundetur in remiſsionem peccatorum,</hi> and wythout any leuacion or lyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng vp.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:22944:11"/>
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London,</hi> the eyght daie of Marche, in the ſecond yere of the reigne of our ſouereigne lorde kyng Edvvard the. VI: By Rychard Grafton printer to his moste royall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie.</p>
            <p>In the yere of our Lorde.</p>
            <p>M. D. XLVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22944:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
